hello everybody Welcome to the BNB
connection this is episode 8 uh with
Brad shonfeld and myself Brett conteras
it's been a while we took a a what
probably a three Monon lapse Brad or
when was the last one we did short high
this was probably about three or four
months y yeah I kept emailing Brad and
he just kept saying he's too busy he
doesn't have time for you
guys um apparently he's gotten really
popular
okay that's not really
true I was the one who was
busy anyway this uh Edition is going to
be on functional
training and Brad and I have been
meaning to do this for a while because
we get so annoyed over these assumptions
and not just the assumptions the
misguided um the the inaccuracies about
the beliefs out there with with strain
coaches and personal trainers pertaining
to functional
training um and so briad and I come
across this all the
time where you'll see a coach just
assumes that say like a free weight
squat is the end all be all it's going
to transfer maximally to everything and
if you do a a machine or some other
movement it doesn't have any effects
whatsoever and it's completely
nonfunctional meaning it won't do
anything for performance
and that doesn't line up with the
research so Brad and my position do you
want to State our position
Brad yeah and I think it goes back
towards uh the article that I wrote back
in I think it was 2010 or 11 for ACSM
where uh functional it's not functional
or non-functional is a binary choice but
rather functional fitness exists on a
Continuum where some exercises are more
functional than others depending on a
number one the individual and a number
two the task requirement you have to
consider both of them before you can
consider what is a functional or more
functional exercise and that as a
general rule exercises there is pretty
much no such thing as a non-functional I
guess there could be if it reduces a a
given motor pattern that is inherent to
the functional thing you want to
accomplish but for the most part you
want to look at functionality on a
Continuum where there's gradations of
transfer now we could talk for several
hours on this topic if we expanded it to
everything but we're going to try to
hone in on exercises on on typical
resistance exercis because we could we
could talk about modes of contraction
like isometric versus you know
concentric versus Ecentric velocity
specificity um God so many different
things isokinetic versus you know
isoinertial and all this stuff
but what most people the biggest topic
the biggest uh Mis misguided um concept
out there is pertaining to exercise
selection and so we have there's a lot
of studies that look at like one one
thing like say the effects of squatting
on whatever on performance there's
probably like 30 studies right now
looking at the squat there's a lot of
studies looking at the O Olympic lifts
uh and their transfer to Performance but
there are not too many comparing
different things like comparing squats
to leg extensions or squats versus leg
press or squats plus leg extensions
versus squats alone or something like
that so a lot of our knowledge is just
speculative but if you're going to be
evidence-based and speculate according
to the literature then you need to get
it right and we feel that most most
coaches just are completely ignorant and
naive to to what to to true Sport
Science and what really is happening
when you when you perform uh resistance
training so we will roll through some of
the studies try and keep it brief and
then we will give an overview
here all right the first
study
um Brad you want to talk about the uh
nonog generian study this is
a what's the name of this this is the
first study um was published in 1990
in the
JAMA the title is high-intensity
strength training in
nonagenarians Brad what is a
nonagenarian that's someone who's 90
years plus so their average age of the
subjects was 90
years okay so Brad give us the overview
on that study yeah and this really to me
is the classic study to show that there
is a functional fitness Continuum and
that you don't want to look at exercises
as functional or nonfunctional so what
they did was they took a group of
nursing home patients there were 10
nursing home patients non- generas 90
years old most of them obviously had
very poor functionality and they put
them on 8 weeks of leg extension
training can't think of any exercise
that would be considered less functional
than a leg extension you're sitting in a
chair just moving your your leg up and
down your lower leg and they did three
sets of eight three times a week and
they did it for eight weeks after the
8-week period the average increase in
strength was around 17 lower body
strength
175% and the average Improvement in
functional ability measures of walking
and other functional tasks was around
50% but here here's what really to me
jumps out two of the 10 subjects were
able to ditch their canes and walk
without the assistance of their cans I
don't know of any thing that is probably
more functional than the ability to walk
without assistance and one of the
subjects was able to get out of the
chair without using their arms so
basically just rise up someone who could
not before needed to push up out of the
chair to get out of the chair was able
to get out of a chair without the use of
doing it with their arms so to me that
is you can't have much better functional
transfer there functional improvements
and really what it shows to me very
clearly is that just increasing strength
regardless of the modality
has and depending on the individual of
course can have huge improvements in
functional
transfer now did one of the subjects
pull off a backflip or did I read that
wrong don't recall seeing that but you
might be right there so Brad this
implies that um now had they done had
they done you know assisted box squats
and then tried to eventually move to
regular boss squats maybe it would have
been better the results might have been
better but that's not the point the
point was to say basic leg extensions
improved functional performance big
time so
this um this implies that just
strengthening the muscle just
strengthening the quadriceps because the
leg extension focuses everything on the
vases and the rectus
florus and so just strengthening those
four
muscles um you know you're going to get
increases in neural activation increases
in hypertrophy which lead to increases
in strength and that leads to functional
performance
improvements um so if now if they would
have done say box squats or something
like that maybe it would have been
better but that doesn't mean leg
extensions wouldn't even if that study
did take place that doesn't mean leg
extensions are worthless because that
doesn't mean that box squats plus leg
extensions wouldn't see even better
improvements so all right that wraps up
and let me Al just add one thing to that
too I I would also or two things
actually number one I would say that I
would doubt that those given the
deconditioned state of those people that
probably the squat would have been a
good movement or certainly like a box
squat that they would have been able to
accomplish that without huge degrees of
assistance so when you talk assistance
so again that's it's arguable but it
might not be a lot of times a
progression basically you're uh
regressing to move to be able to
progress uh that you can take it that
and and again I think just more to your
point is is that really what this shows
is is that we shouldn't look at exercis
as as non-functional that it's not that
an exercise well that's there we do a
machine it's not we don't move that way
so it's nonfunctional that's really just
a silly way to look at
things okay next study we will talk
about is uh the effect of of open and
closed kinetic chain exercises on
dynamic balance ability of normal
healthy adults Brad do you remember this
one yeah I do uh they looked at um an
open and chain movements they did a
dynamic balance task where it was a
diagonal step one way to the left and
then to the right and what they found in
in summary was that the both open and
chain and closed chain movements did
produce improvements in in dynamic
balance but that the closed chain had
somewhat greater improvements so it
wasn't that there was no transfer from
the open chain but that as you would
expect there is a that Continuum and you
did see greater dynamic balance
improvements in the close chain and as
again at the important Point as you said
they did not look at a combination of
open and closed chain which to me is
look at one thing and we can talk about
this a little more at the end but
bodybuilding is often thought of as a
non functional type of trading system
where bodybuilders use both uh free
weight type moves closed chain free
weight moves as well as open chain
machines and and combinations of such so
to to say that it is nonfunctional well
they're using combinations of these and
that has never been looked at to the
best of my
knowledge even powerlifters will use
assistance exercises so um okay so take
on point there
is if you have to choose between open
and closed kinetic chain exercises and
your goal is to improve balance then
closed chain exercise are going to be
better but you might see the best
results doing a combination of training
that hasn't been looked at okay by the
way one thing I think that was good
about this study is they looked at
dynamic balance rather than static
balance which is generally what most
studies look at they look at static
standing on one leg and obviously or I
would think obviously that the dynamic
balance in most functional task is the
more important variable than static
balance most people if they're going to
need balance it's during Dynamic
movement not
during uh during quiet standing yep
agree all right next paper specificity
of machine barbell and water filled log
bench press resistance training on
measures of
strength um this was 2007
jscr
um
and this one
uh Bradley this one they gave uh they
had subjects either do machine bench
press barbell bench press or log log
bench
press and they looked at what was nice
about this is they looked at the
transfer to each
type well so if your functional goal is
to just
bench the most weight well it depends on
what type of bench if you want to log
press log log bench the most weight then
the study showed that you should use a
log if you wanted to machine bench the
most weight then you got the best
results from doing machine bench press
if you want to bench press the most
weight you got the best results out of
the barbell um barbell bench press which
makes sense with specificity but the
take home point is that they all
transferred to each other so and there
were no statistic uh statistical
significance between between um all of
the three
variations however if you just kind of
look at the chart and don't look at
statistical significant you can you can
see that specificity occurred you did
get more strength gains if your so if
your goal is to to gain the most on
barbell bench press then you would do
barbell bench press but machine and log
bench still transfer to barbell and they
all transfer each other they also looked
at just bench press Force production and
the barbell saw the best improvements
but again they didn't do combine a
combination of them and it does show
that everything trans everything
transfers everything is functional it's
just that some things are better than
others two two things here Brett as you
pointed out I do think the fact that
they didn't look at combinations and and
I wouldn't think they could it's just
obviously in a research study it gets
very difficult to uh to control to have
that type of to to carry out studies
where you're looking at that many
subjects so I certainly I understand the
limitations but you can make a case that
increasing hypertrophy that a
combination of machines which might
Target more in certain aspects of the CH
chest combined with the neural aspects
of a free weight bench might transfer
better because increased muscle
hypertrophy does show there is a a clear
Rel relationship between cross-sectional
area and force production I also do want
to point out though that an upper body I
would also posit that an upper body
exercise is not as the functional
transfer is not as great as the lower
body and I can tell you from experience
on the study I just carried out um where
we had some of the subjects they were
all resistance trained subjects but some
of them just the lower body did the leg
cresses and leg extensions and they had
the biggest increases in the squat there
were very large differences in many of
the cases there I think we had four
subjects who didn't Squat and um you do
see great because the squat is a much
more complex move than a bench press
you're going to see greater than
transfer and just the coordination of
that movement from a machine to a actal
freway movement however if we're going
to be consistent with this like this
looked at three different bench presses
this way if you did three different
types of squats
like a barbell squat versus a lever
machine squat versus a log filled you
know water filled log squat my guess you
you would it would be the same as this
study but like if you did pec deck and
tricep extension you're not going to see
that much gains in bench press strength
compared to on I would disagree with you
because there's a much greater balance
appropri acceptive aspect to a squat
than there is a bench press so I do
think that now I agree there probably
would be less variation than from a leg
press but I do think you'd see that
again it goes back to a Continuum where
I think the leg press would be much
further down on the Contin no I'm not
talking leg press I'm saying like a like
a squat barbell squat a log Squat and
then like a lever machine squat but if
you did leg press and leg extensions
they're not going to transfer the squat
as much
but I do think that you wouldn't see the
same my point is with a lever machine
squat versus a regular squat I think you
would see less transfer than a bench
press to a machine bench press reg
barbell to a machine just because of the
propri acceptive aspects of being able
to maintain balance in three-dimensional
space whereas a bench pressure lying
down and just pushing up with a barbell
and one you still have three dimensions
but it's there's much less of a balance
it's not as complicated right right
right but I would agree with you on your
premise earlier that if you did squats
and lever squats in the same session say
twice a week you might be able to get
even better gains than if you just did
one or the other because the benefits of
the lever machine or that you can
control trunk angle really you can you
know you can control and you don't have
to worry about balance you can just
worry about Force
production and um which might lead to
you know more hypertrophy of a certain
muscle or you know they they might have
synergistic effects that has not been
looked at yet Brad and I want to do some
of this research as time goes on yeah
that's so your exact point and that's
we've talked we're just waiting for Brad
to get his PhD so we can carry out some
of this research
he's lagging on actually so one of the
studies that Brett and I actually will
be looking at and I this is on my my
plate my very full plate at this point
but it's going to happen is uh looking
at six sets of squats six sets of leg
presses or three set squats three set
leg presses and looking to see what
theun transfer my thought certainly my
hypothesis would be that as long as
you're getting the squatting in doing
the additional s you'd have greater uh
greater results from adding in some
light presses rather than just doing the
full six sets of squats as long as
you're getting those three sets that's
enough for the neural adaptations where
you can then see greater results by
adding in some
additional my that's my hypothesis too
and my same hypothesis
my thesis for my PhD is uh going to look
at squats versus hip thrust versus
squats plus hip thrust so it's the same
study as yours but instead of leg
extensions hip thrusts and I thought of
it thrat are nonfunctional so yeah right
and I thought of it before you so you
stole my
idea okay
um going finishing off here we've got
two more to talk about
this next one is strength outcomes in
fixed versus free form resistance
equipment this was jscr
2008 and Brad talk about this
one yeah that was the spenn study you're
talking about yeah so what spanin did
was he looked at and this was actually
an interesting study he looked at um
machines your fix machines which only
move in one plane of movement versus a
free for machine like the free motion
equipment cable type apparatus which
move in three dimensional planes and he
did a full body workout looking at all
the working all the major muscle groups
and the bottom line was that he did a
tests of strength and balance and the
strength test uh they showed if I recall
you might correct me on this but about
was it was about I remember that you got
significant I don't remember the exact
amount but there was substantial
increases in strength significant and
substantial increases in and strengthen
the fixed movements but the free form
movements had roughly double it was like
50% versus 100% somewhere in their
increases in strength where the free
form actually had double the increases
and with balance now the so we'll talk
about the issues with the balance but
balance showed about 50% increases with
the free form but there was 25th so it
was a five-fold increase in the uh free
form equipment it
was 57% % increase in strength from the
fixed from the machine training 115%
from the free form 49% inbalance in the
machines and 245 per inbalance in the
free form yeah now the the issue was is
that first of all the testing for the
strength I believe was on a free form
wasn't it on no no this is my problem
with the stud is it was in their various
so that the machines they
increased they they used machines to
test for the pre and post were for
machine group and then the free form did
pre and post with the free form and it's
like it reminds me of the first time I
did
uh the first time my friend Chad
Waterberry tried to show me ring dips
and I could do a dip
with with like 3 45s and a 25 I mean
that's what 13
one6 I can do 160 lb weighted dip but I
could not do one ring dip it was so hard
for me and after like you know 10
minutes of practice I finally got to
where I could do two of them but it's so
unstable it's a whole different thing
you know and the this so the free motion
had way better you're going to start out
with that and you're going to be so in
coordinated and you're going to get way
better at it through intermuscular
coordination gains so I feel like that
was I would have if I were a peer
reviewer for that study I would have had
a hard you know a hard time with that
because
it would just uh you know the the
machine group it's not as coordinative
so you just push you don't have to
coordinate as much so you don't have as
much room to gain so I don't like that
and also the balance test was on a
standing on a bosu ball with the Dome up
and I don't you know I don't think
that's as functional as people think and
that's what we mentioned before is that
if you're going to look it balance
really dynamic balance quiet balance
standing on one leg on a bosu I'm not
sure what the functional transfer is you
could call that a test of balance which
it is but how much does that transfer to
functional task that's something
supect okay and then last paper we will
talk about this is a really good paper
this is by blazovich this is called uh
training specific muscle architecture
adaptation after five weeks of training
in
athletes um this was uh published in the
medicine and Science and Sport an ex
Sports and exercise Journal uh what year
was this this
was while back this was
uh date
here
2003 and this study looked at they had
one group just did sprinting and jumping
one group added in if you can see on the
computer screen here this forward hack
squat one-legged forward hack
squat uh where they're standing
backwards on the hack squat machine
doing a one-legged hack Squat and the
other group did squats and this was a
very interesting article because you
look at the charts there were so there
were no they looked at all sorts of
things they looked at 10 and 20 meter
Sprints one and two-legged vertical
jumps they looked at all kinds of force
production and you know different speeds
and things like
that however they showed no significant
differences but if if you go in and look
at the charts what was interesting is
that
the the forward hack squat group
actually saw the saw better gains in
sprinting than the squat group but the
squat group saw better gains than the
vertical jump group and then of course
if you looking at squat force the squat
group saw better gains in
squatting and so this but even the like
um the fical length and angle changes
were identical between the forward hack
Squat and the squat group um so and was
interesting the group that did not do
any weight training actually increased
their fasal length and angle um which
was interesting because they ceased
strength training but that's kind of
outside the scope of this discussion but
anyway the point
is if it would make sense that you'd see
better results you know oh and they did
supplementary exercises too they did
back extensions leg curls and cal rais
machine C raises and so according to
most strength coaches out there the the
group that did the forward hack squat
was a machine exercise the back
extension is non-standing you're in an
apparatus the the the leg curl is
nonfunctional according to most coaches
the standing Cal raises in a machine and
they they improved performance they got
faster and this just goes to show you
and they got faster than the squat group
did these are trained athletes too yeah
and these are trained athletes and then
the squat group The Squat group saw
better jumping gain so if you combined
the the theoretically speaking if you
combine now this was a short study it
was only five weeks but still if you
combine the forward the unilateral
forward hack Squat and the squat study
the sorry the squat squatting then you
might have seen even better results so
this just goes to show you that as we
stated earlier functional training is on
a Continuum it's not like this is
completely this is the end all be all
and you get your you know functional
capacity goes through the roof doing
this but if you do this it goes down or
doesn't change at all it's a Continuum
and some things are better for certain
things than others the the law of
specificity applies but combined
training can give you better results so
um so now that we've discussed the
Articles there's a lot of review review
good review papers on the topic too and
we will link these in the blog post but
now let's just discuss functional
training um and kind of the the
ramifications of these uh these studies
so my biggest problem Brad is that most
clients you know I think that I probably
trained a thousand people in my
lifetime and I I would say 900 of them
came to me primarily for to look better
for physique enhancement right what
would you say the percentages with you
you you trained thousands of people
my I came up with the phrase look great
naked because that was 90% of my clients
were coming in saying I really don't
care what do you want to do I just want
to look better I want I want to look
good without my clothes on I don't
really care about the health and and
obviously that's important to them when
they really thought about it but most
people are very aesthetically based and
know as you get people get older so yeah
when you're 70 you're not looking to the
bikini years probably are behind you or
the tank top that's not what your your
focus is at that point but certainly in
your younger sex certainly under 50 I
would say when under 50 the vast
majority are are aesthetically driven
and most people don't come in and say
you know my goal is to increase but like
vertical jump or my you know 40 met dash
time but my ability to carry my now
again you would get some people I want
to carry my child but that those are
those are secondary considerations
there's added benefits but the point is
you like let's say you
incorporate you uh you know and some
machines or apparatuses let you target
strength curves that you can't get with
free weights a lot of free weight
movements they have torque angle curves
that dissipate at end range and so you
you need to add in these other things
for bounce well for example if you just
squatted if you just did squats that was
your only lower body exercise first of
all not going to strengthen the
hamstrings uh optimally and second of
all you're not going to get end range
hip extension strength you'll get
initial Flex range hip extension
strength you'll build the quadriceps
very well you'll build up the glutes you
won't build up glute strength at in
range you won't build the hamstring
strength so you need supplemental
exercises to optimize performance here
um and so yeah if I can add in there the
many your biarticular many biarticular M
muscles need targeted training need
single joint training to optimize the
length tension relationship your gastric
nemas your hamstrings your erectus
femoris biceps break eye L head of the
triceps all of them are at a an impaired
uh length tension through various ranges
of multi-joint movements and really
unless you put them in a position where
you fix them at the at one end while
you're training them at the other you're
not going to optimally develop that
muscle both from a strengthen and
hypertrophy standpoint so and my another
thing I wanted to talk about
like it blows my mind when these people
act like you can you know you can only
these Co coaches and trainers out there
they clearly haven't studied the
literature because the lack like this is
a worthless you know ex you know fill in
whatever you because Brad one thing
about you and I we never you'll never
hear us say that this exercise is
useless we'll we've never said that but
I've heard this say I've heard people
say you should not squat you should not
deadlift you should not bench press you
should not do leg extensions you should
not do leg press you should not do bend
over rows you should not do dips you
should not do military press you should
not do chin-ups you should not do hip
thrusts you should not do lunges you
should not do lying leg curls um you
should not do crunches you should not do
sit-ups um God the list goes on you
should not do kall swings the the
Olympic lifts the list goes on and on
and so we need to have some sort of
objective way of discussing you know
certainly Anatomy comes into play and
you got to learn good form not every
human being is meant to do Rock Bottom
full
squats but they can still squat you know
I've I've squatted every client I've
ever trained did some type of squat they
did hip thrust they did some form of
deadlifting they might not be able to do
um you know deadlifts from the floor or
like deficit deadlifts they might not be
able to do you know Rock Bottom astig
grass squats but they could do high box
squats or goblet squats or something you
know so but my my point is you you get
better results from doing more than one
exercise like no I don't see who would
argue that you can only just do one
exercise so it's not about not doing
this it's about you know adhering to a
well-rounded routine so if and the next
thing is let me just add though it's
also looking at the principle of
individual differences Central tenant of
training uh
suggests that some exercise for certain
people might not be the best solution
and that you have to look at the
person's body habitats and other factors
and also what are they looking to
accomplish you're going to train an
athlete I think one real important Point
here is that we try we'll take people
and strength coaches will try to take
the training of athletes and apply them
to your everyday people and your
everyday people are not athletes and
they don't have the same goals for most
people their task requirements are very
very very slight so what they're going
to need to do the the types of training
you're going to need to do to make them
uh able to complete their activities of
daily living goes nowhere near what you
would need for an athlete and it it
really is overkill how many people need
to live Boulders I guess there might be
people who are moving their or or
populating their lawn doing landscaping
and they lifting heav in that case maybe
doing Boulder lift strength basic
strength moves your strong man type
moves might be appropriate for them to
optimize their test but your your stock
broker your mom your new new mom the
vast majority of people certainly that
all of us have trained have very modest
task requirements and that you're the
generalized training is going to get
them if they're looking to get if their
goal is to get aesthetically better
that's going to help them to achieve
what basically whatever they need to
achieve in their everyday tasks so you
have to really analyze now if they have
other um goals if their if their goals
are to hike Mount Everest you'd have
obviously you put uh other types of
training in there but for again the vast
majority just to to use again a a catch
all of functional fitness functional
fitness is specific to the person what
are their functional goals and needs
it's not there's a functional fitness
that everyone needs to achieve a certain
degree of function it's kind of silly
now to piggy back off what Brad's saying
think of my situation most of my clients
come to me wanting glutes they are not
happy with their glute development
they've tried other routines if the if
the previous routine worked for them
they wouldn't have found me because they
wouldn't be typing into Google you know
how to get nice glutes or something like
that and so they find me and their goal
is glutes and I give them I prioritize
glute development and so they will
notice once they prioritize their glutes
they start noticing all sorts of
functional improvements but that's my
original goal was just to help them grow
glutes but they start saying I'm
sprinting
faster um I'm I I'm you know carrying my
groceries up you know three flights of
stairs no problem I'm hiking better I'm
running F uh you know doing my
longdistance run and they
improved um my low back pain is is went
away my knee pain went away my hip pain
went away things like that and those are
those are all functional side effects
but you know it's it's from a well
balance comprehensive glute training
routine in which case you're going to do
a lot of exercis that might not appear
functional for example look at the hip
thrust you're on the ground with a bar
in your lap humping up and down well
does that transfer the performance hell
yeah it does you're hip thrusting you're
strengthening the glutes at end range
hip extension that's the same range of
motion where it associated with ground
contact in running in sprinting so if
you're also sprinting and this is
another thing whatever your goal if you
have a performance goal in mind you
better be doing that activity for
example if you want to squat the most
weight you need to be squatting if
powerlifting is your goal you're going
to be doing squats bench and
deadlifts now some guys who have
shoulder issues will do a lot of their
training with a safety squat bar or
something like that or a Swiss bar with
bench press but then right before the
meet they'll switch to a couple weeks of
specificity and that's to preserve their
joints but the point is you want to be
doing specificity if your goal is to
Sprint as fast as possible you better be
doing sprints that's the most important
part of it but you add in these other
things and it's going to help Will
adding in hip thrust help yeah they will
well adding in um cable exercises you
know they're not free weighs but you can
train different you know rotational
patterns and things like that that can
build core and glute strength as a hip
external Rotator and they can help you
twist faster when you do in your
rotational sport throw faster swing
harder and so to me you want to look at
all these things and you want to make
sure you're doing a well balanced
routine and it all depends on the goals
of the lifter of course you don't want
to be doing dangerous exercises that are
going to drive this person into the
ground and not and not let him keep
training but if you vary things and you
have good form there's a lot of
different options and there's a lot of
ways to to you know put together an
effective strength and conditioning
program that helps the person achieve
their goals improves their function and
keeps them
healthy I
agree all right Bradley do you have
anything else to add well just again I
think it's real important to reiterate
that functional transfer it's not a
binary functional versus non-functional
that it exists on a Continuum that
really the astute Fitness Pro is going
to take into account the need and
abilities of the individual as well as
the task requirements uh and then create
their plan accordingly and I would say
that for the vast majority of people the
thought of functional fitness while it
sounds very cool and and create it's a
nice buzzword that just general type
training where you're combining
exercises and even bodybuilding training
that movements over muscles really
doesn't for for an athlete yeah that's
where you're going to start to see that
but uh for the vast majority training in
a body body building type routine well
I've never seen a bodybuilder uh that
cannot lift the package or lift the baby
and do functional Tas so uh I I think
highly overblown if the bodybuilders
don't lose flexibility like people think
but they're on a lot of different drugs
that help them grow to massive
proportions that's not going to happen
with other people their flexibility is
impaired because their muscles are so
large that they can't move through full
range of motion that's yeah that is not
the most people are not going to have
that problem you and I don't have that
problem Brad and I do well my my problem
is why would you not want to that's as
far as I go here it's just stand biceps
and come
up you're imaginary lat syndrome is
pretty apparent right now but uh why
would you not look I've never understood
this because as a I'm you know as a
personal trainer I've always wanted to
know I've been I'm Mar at what the
Olympic lifters do and they do things
very differently you know depending on
the country but I want to know how they
train because they're the most powerful
individuals in the world right I want to
know how the track and field athletes
train which is kind of funny because a
lot of the Jamaican team they do their
Sprints and their plios and sled work
and then they go in the weight room and
do a lot of machines a lot of coaches
would be like that's you know so stupid
and that's they the fastest Runners you
know sprinters in the world
but uh um because they have it right
they realize with sprinting you need to
Sprint a lot and kind of stay fresh and
then just get the muscles stronger in
the right ranges they'll do cable hip
flexion they'll do the glute you know um
quadrip glute Blaster machine where
you're just kicking your leg upward it's
similar to hip thrust where you're
strengthening end range hip extension
strength but you know they're not
prioritizing heavy barbell strength but
it works for them I want to know what
the body builders are doing they're the
masters of hypertrophy they know how to
get bigger and they know it better than
anyone I want to know what the
powerlifters are doing they know to
increase bench Squat and deadlift great
better than anyone and you can apply
what they know about strength
development to the other lifts too you
know they know how to do maximal effort
training submaximal effort training
Dynamic effort you know training and
doing all these you know specificity but
also some variety with your supplemental
and accessory lifts and they know how to
get strong but the they will they will
if you listen to a pter they'll say the
squat the deadlift and the bench are
here and everything else is rendered as
an Assistance or supplementary but for
them that's true because all they need
to do is the squad F but if you're an
athlete if your goal from a functional
transfer standpoint that's the case for
for their lifts that's all they're
required to get good in the squat dead
lift and and Ben so that's for them all
there is but if your goal is glute
development you're you might have three
three Li other lifts that are the core
lifts and these are all supplementary
accessory or if your goal is to hit a
baseball as far as possible you might
pick these to be your Three core lifts
so it depends on your goal it depends on
you know if if your goal is physique
versus functional you know if it's high
performance or just basic walking or
whatever so learn from the different
camps learn from the strongmen the
Olympic weightlifters the bodybuilders
um the powerlifters the athletes the
different types of athletes and Olympic
you know um uh Sports and how they train
and pick up pieces from all of it it all
helps and when you train when you do
personal training I can tell you the
more methods you know of the bigger tool
set you have you might stick most of the
time to these 10 movements but when you
utilize other approaches when you have
them push a Prowler when you have them
doing you know some some pios or stuff
like that when you add in some of this
stuff they like it you get more clients
when you do hip thrust and that the
clients start developing glutes they
like it they refer other people and then
you have more you know and everyone's
happy you get more clients they see
better results Word of Mouth spreads
I've never understood this um in the
fitness you know out there on the inter
interwebs you will see so many people
bashing methods and and um you know
Effective modalities Thinking and that
goes to this and it goes to other just
general it pervades the industry a lot
it's it's do this you either do this or
that there's no in between and it's just
a silly way to look at training it's uh
you will you will never achieve your
optimal goals unless you take a
broad-based approach and look to combin
methods to me the the thought of of this
or that is not only Antiquated it's
misguided so agree okay that concludes
episode eight is it eight episode eight
um again we apologize for taking so long
to come out with a new one um but we
hope you enjoyed listening to this one
thank you for watching